Hello, and welcome back. We just finished learning about curve
【未完成版本】大家好 欢迎回来 我们刚刚学习过了曲线演化
evolution. There's one thing that is missing that we
还有一个知识点我们刚刚略过了是需要学习的
need to learn. It's how do we implement curve evolution
那就是我们如何在计算机上实现曲线演化
in the computer. We saw that curve evolution is important
我们已经知道曲线演化是很重要的
for example, to regularize curves with curvature motion, but even more important
例如使用配合曲率运动来调控曲线 在主动轮廓中则有更重要的作用
for active contours. And we need to learn, how do we implement
我们也需要学习
in that friendly fashion that in a computer we have discrete images.
如何用一种友好的形式将其实现出来 因为在计算机中只有离散图像
So, we need to talk about the numerical implementation of that.
所以我们将会谈谈它的数值实现
one of the areas that has had a tremendous impact in image processing, in
当我们讲解偏微分方程在图像处理中的应用时
particular, when we talk about PDs in image processing, is level sets methods
有一个对于图像处理有着极大影响的领域 也就是水平集方法
and I want to to explain that. And with that, we're going to know how we
我们来谈谈这个方法 有了这个方法 我们将会知道
implement any type of curve or surface evolution in a computer.
如何将任意曲线曲面演化在计算机中实现出来
So what is all this theory, all this framework of level sets?
那么水平集的理论和框架是什么呢？
So we have talk about curves and it's going to be the same for surfaces because
我们来讨论一下曲线的情况 因为曲线的情况相对曲面来讲简单许多
it's much easier to present this for curves.
不过曲面情况的原理是差不多的
We have talk about curves and curve representations.
我们已经谈过曲线以及曲线的表示
And we see that here, we have a curve that is parameterized and remember for
这里我们可以看到 这是一条已经参数方程化的曲线
every P, we have basically a different point on the curve.
对于每一个 p 都对应着曲线上不同的点
Now this is not the only way to represent curves.
不过现在这不是唯一能表示曲线的方法了
There's a very different way to represent exactly the same curve that is actually
还有一种非常不同的方法可以表示完全相同的一条曲线
even more familiar when we are talking about shapes.
实际上当我们讨论形状的时候我们会更熟悉它
And the basic idea is that instead of parameterizing the curve, we're going to
它的基本原理 并不参数方程化曲线
represent the curve by all the points on the plane that hold a certain equation
而是将曲线表达为 平面上所有使得特定方程等于 0 的点
equal to zero. So let's look at this figure.
让我们来看看这张图片
We're going to put a coordinate system x and y and then we say every point in the
我们在这里放下一个坐标系 x 和 y 然后我们说
curve is a point such that phi at that point is equal to zero.
所有在曲线上的点都使得函数 phi 在这个点的值为 0
So we have to describe this function phi. And for example we can define the
那么我们得描述这个函数 phi 例如 我们可以定义
function to be positive inside and negative outside and one example is to
内部的点使得函数的值为正 外部的点则使得函数的值为负
define this as the distance to the curve for, for of course the distance to the
比如我们可以定义这是到曲线的距离
curve at the curve itself is zero. The distance to the point itself is zero.
显然曲线到自身的距离为 0 因为一个点到自己的距离为 0
So, every point on the curve has zero distance to the curve.
所以 所有在曲线上的点到曲线的距离都是 0
Every point inside has a positive distance, and we define every point
所有内部的点都有着大于 0 的距离
outside to be at negative distance. And that way, we define the function phi.
并且我们定义外部的点有着小于 0 距离 用这种方式 我们可以定义函数 phi
That the zero set, that's called the zero level set of that function, meaning all
这个零集合被叫做这个函数的零水平集
the points in the plain where that function is zero define a curve.
表示使得这个函数值为 0 的所有平面上的点定义的一条曲线
Let's look at a profile of this and we see that here. If I have a function that
让我们来看看这里的这个剖面
is positive inside and negative outside and I cross it with a line, then this is
如果我们有一个函数是里面是正的外面是负的 我用一条直线剖开它
the profile. We're going from negative tp positive.
那就可以得到一个剖面 函数从负值变化到正值
So this region is positive. Then we go again outside, so we have
所以这个区域都是正的 接下来又到了外面
negative again. And we go again inside and we go again
所以又变成了负值 之后又进入到内部 然后又到了外部
outside. Now which are the points that belong to
那么 哪些点是在曲线上的呢？
the curve. This point, basically, this zero.
这个点 它是 0
This point and this point and this point, every time the profile of five crosses
这个点 这个点 还有这个点 剖面的 phi 函数每一次经过 0 线的时候
the zero, that point belongs to the surface.
对应的那个点就是在曲面上的
In that way we are, belongs to a curve sorry or a surface if we are in higher
这样 啊 不好意思 应该是在曲线上 当然如果在更高维度下这就是曲面了
dimensions. In that case, in that form we are
这样 我们就用这种使得某个函数的值为 0 的形式
defining a curve on the plane by all the points that hold this equal to zero.
定义了平面上的曲线
And these two are just two different representations of exactly the same
这只是两种对同一条曲线的不同表达
curve. This is kind of painting inside the curve
这就好像在曲线内部涂色
and painting outside the curve in such a way that along the curve that paint is
和在曲线外部涂色
equal to zero. Now.
而在曲线上涂的就是等于 0
With this representation we have compute tangents, normals and curvature.
现在有了这种表示方法 我们还得计算切线、法线和曲率
We need to be able to compute it with this representation, otherwise, we won't
我们需要用这种表达来计算它们
be able to do curve evolution. So let's see how we do that.
否则我们没法做曲线演化 让我们来学习这些内容
And we're going to prove a couple of things.
我们需要先证明一些东西
As we have talked, this week is one of the most theoretical ones.
就像我之前提过的 这周的课程是最理论化的一周了
But we are doing everything self-contained.
不过我们要讲的都是自含的
So I'm explaining everything inside and I think we are learning a lot of new
那么我来讲讲里面发生的事情 我觉得我们学了挺多的新概念了
concepts. So let us show that basically if we
那我们就开始讲解这个
define the curve as before at the zero level set of the function fee.
当然如前所述 曲线是由函数 phi 的水平集来定义的
The normal is the gradient of phi divided by the magnitude, actually, with a minus.
法线实际上就是 phi 的梯度除以幅度 当然还要加上负号
That's a convention because I want the normal to point inwards.
这是一个惯例 因为我们需要法线是朝里面的
It's just a convention. And of course the tangent will be this.
这只是个惯例 接下来切线自然就是这个了
It's basically a perpendicular vector. Let's prove that, it's not hard to prove.
这是一个垂直向量 让我们来证明这个 这证明起来并不困难
So remember, we have the function phi and all the points that belong to the curve
首先 我们有函数 phi 并且所有在曲线上的点都会使得 phi 的值为 0
is where phi is equal to zero. So along the curve, phi is not changing.
所以沿着曲线的话 phi 的值是不会变化的
It's always zero. When I travel the curve, it's always
它总是 0 如果我沿着曲线走 总会得到 0
zero. Then, the derivative of the function
那么 函数的导数就是沿着曲线的
along the curve. Along the arc length.
沿着弧长
Because I'm traveling along the curve is equal to zero.
因为我们是沿着函数值为 0 的曲线走
Let's compute that derivative. So I want to take the derivative of this
我们来算一下导数 我希望计算这个函数的导数
function. Remember, the function exists all over
请记住 这个函数是存在于整个平面上的
the plane, and I'm taking the derivative in the direction of the curve in the,
我将要求沿着曲线弧长的方向的导数
with the arc length along the curve. Now, we have it here.
那这个就是了
This is just the chain rule. Basic calculus.
这是链式法则 基础微积分
So if I have to take the derivative according to s.
如果我要求对 s 的导数
It's the derivative according to x, x according to s, and the same for the y.
那这个导数就是先对 x 求导数 然后 x 再对 s 求导数 y 是一样的
So that's simple calculus. Now, what I wrote here is this inner
这是一个简单的微积分 接下来 我这里写的是内积
product. Remember, the inner product of two
内积是对两个向量的操作
vectors. So I'm going to write it here in case you
如果大家不太记得的话 我把这个写下来
don't remember. If I want to multiply two vectors a, b.
如果我要把向量两个向量乘起来 这是a、b
I want to do the inner product, let's say with cd is a * c + b Time d.
我实际上是要求内积 那么假如跟c、d相乘 那么就是 a * c + b * d
So this is nothing else, now the inner product of the gradient of phi with the
就是这样 现在这是 phi 的梯度和切线的内积
time chain. Remember, xs, ys is the time chain, is
xs 和 ys 是切线 是单位切线
the unit time chain. We say that a couple of years ago when we
我们之前在谈平面微分几何曲线的时候
were talking about differential geometry curves of the plane.
已经见过这个了
And phi x, phi y is just a gradient. So, this is what we have here.
phi x 和 phi y 只是梯度 这就是为何我们得到了这个
Now this is zero. Okay, we have it here.
那么这个是 0 从这里可以看到
Of course this is the zero. So I'm going to go here.
当然这个也是 0 我们从这里到这里
And, of course, I'm allowed to normalize. So here I have proof that the gradient of
当然 我还可以对它归一化 这样我就证明了
the curve is perpendicular to the tangent.
曲线的梯度是垂直于切线的
Then I normalize the gradient. So if I have a vector that is
然后我们对梯度归一化 如果我有一个跟别的向量垂直的向量
perpendicular to another. Of course, any change in magnitude in the
显然 任何对这个向量进行幅长的变化不会影响垂直的关系
vector is still perpendicular. In particular I want to basically
特别地 我想要把它
normalize it to have unit norm. And then I get this equal to zero.
归一化成单位向量 这个仍然是等于 0 的
So if this is perpendicular to the tangent then this is the normal.
如果这个跟切线垂直 那它自然也就是法线了
So I have a perpendicular, this is the normal.
我们这里是垂直的 所以它就是法线
And now once again, we as a convention put a minus because they, we want if we
再一次地 按照惯例加上一个负号
have positive and negative we want the gradient to point, to point basically we
如果我们区分正负 我们希望这个梯度指向
want the normal to point inwards. Once again, it's just a convention.
我们希望这个法线指向内部 这是个惯例
So a very simple proof that basically shows that.
这样我们就用一个简单的证明展示了这个
This is the definition of a normal so having phi, I can complete the normal
这就是法线的定义 如果我们有了 phi 毫无疑问我们就可以算出法线
with absolutely no problem and of course I can complete the tangent just a
当然我们也可以计算出切线 因为切线跟法线相互垂直
perpendicular vector to it. And we have the first, actually we have
我们有了这个
two. The normal and the tangent.
啊两个 法线和切线
Now let us compute the curvature. And again a very simple computation as we
现在让我们来计算曲率 这也是一个很简单的计算 就像刚刚的那些一样
have here. Just maybe two more steps and we get the
最多就多两三步 我们就能算出曲率
curvature. So what we want to show is that the
我们这里要求的是曲率
curvature, I only have phi, remember the curvature is the second derivative
我们现在只有 phi 函数 曲率是对 s 的二阶导数
according to s. So the curvature was cssKN.
所以曲率就是 这里 Css 等于 K N
equal kN. That's a curvature.
这就是曲率
This is, I want to compute. I don't have c.
这个是我需要计算的 但是我没有C
I have phi. I have c, the curve, the final implicitly
我们只有 phi 函数 我们有 C 也就是曲线
by phi as its zero level set. And I want to prove that it's this
也就是隐含在函数 phi 里的零水平集 我想要证明这就是其对应的公式
formula. In case you don't remember what div is,
有些同学可能不知道 div 是什么
div is a divergence. And the divergence of a vector alpha beta
div 就是散度 一个向量 alpha beta的散度
is basically alpha x + beta y. So it's a scalar.
其实就是alpha x + beta y 所以这是一个标量
The first term of the vector, you take the derivative according to the first
对于向量中的第一维 我们用它对 x 方向求导数
coordinate X. The second, according to the second
对于第二维 我们把它对 y 求导数
coordinate, okay?
好的
Let us prove this formula right now. So now, we are basically, are still going
让我们来证明这个公式是对的
along the zero level set so we still have this relationship.
因为我们还是沿着零水平集 所以我们仍然有这个关系
And let us exploit it now. We are going to compute the second
我们可以利用这个关系
derivative of phi along the curve with arc length.
我们要对 phi 求沿着曲线弧长的二阶导数
We just compute the first one in the previous slide when we're computing the
为了计算法线 我们已经在前一页演示稿里求出了一阶导数
normal. Now I want to compute the second
现在我们要计算二阶导数
derivative. So I have the first derivative and I want
所以我们只需要对一阶导数再求一次导数
to take one more derivative. Now, once again, this was nothing else
这部分其实就是
than the gradient in our product with T as we saw the previous one and I have to
梯度和 T 的内积 我们之前已经见过了 我们现在要对这个求导数
take a derivative. Remember derivative of a final product is
内积的导数实际上就是
the derivative of the first times the second plus the first times derivative of
第一个分量的导数乘以第二个分量 再加上第一个分量乘以第二个分量的导数
the second. Now what's the derivative of the tangent?
那切线的导数是什么呢？
Second derivative is curvature in a normal direction.
二阶导数是在法线方向上的曲率
So here it is. Curvature in a normal direction.
那这里也就是在法线方向上的曲率
So once again, derivative of the first one times inner product with the tangent
再来一次 第一个分量与切线的内积
and then the first one, inner product with the derivative of the second one,
和第一个分量与第二个分量的导数的内积
which is T. But we know that the derivative of T is
第二个分量实际上就是 T 我们还知道 T 的导数是 kN
kN and this basically is equal to zero. So what we have, so this is equal to
并且因为这个是等于 0 的 所以我们这里其实也是等于 0 的
zero, so what we have is that this turn is equal to minus distant and basically I
那么就变成了 这一项的等于这一项
wrote that here so this turn I can take the curvature outside,
我把这个写在下面了 我们可以把曲率提出来
okay? That's not a problem.
这没有任何问题
It's a scalar. I can take it outside of the inner
因为它是一个标量 我们可以把它从内积中提出来
product. That's the first thing we do.
这是我们要做的第一件事
Oh, I apologize, there is here a typo, this should be a phi.
噢 不好意思 这里有个笔误 这个应该是 phi
Basically a kind of a capital phi, but, I apologize for that typo.
应该是一个大写的 phi 不好意思打错了
We are going to continue. It's just that very easy to see that
我们继续 很容易看出来
going from here I just made a typo. And we basically have the curvature goes
这一步有个笔误 我们把曲率提取出来了
outside, that's here, then we have this, again here.
把它放在这里 然后这个对应这个
And the normal we just saw in the previous slide, is gradient divided by
我们在前一页见过 法线是梯度除以梯度(的模)
gradient. So we have curvature here.
那么我们就得到了曲率
Now this product is the gradient square because I'm multiplying this by itself.
现在这个积实际上是梯度的平方 因为我们这里让它乘上了自己
So it's the gradient square divided by the gradient that cancel each other and I
所以这是梯度的平方除以梯度(的模) 其中一个梯度被抵消了
get only one gradient. So this turn.
我们就剩下一个梯度(的模) 所以这一项就是这个
Is here, okay? This term I'm not going to write it down
我没有把这一项写下来
but by now you're an expert because we're just doing derivatives and chain rule.
但是现在同学们已经是专家啦 因为我们只要求导数和链式法则就可以了
If you want to take the derivative of the gradient according to S, remember you
如果我们要求梯度对 s 的导数
have to take the derivative according to X and then XS plus derivative according
我们只要求它对 x 的导数然后 xs 加上对 y 的导数 以及 ys
to y, ys. So you do chain rule again and then
【未完成版本】我们只要再做一遍链式法则
you're going to get this expression. This expression is basically this
然后就可以得到这个表达式 这个表达式其实就是它的导数
derivative. And then the tangent once again we have
然后切线我们之前已经得到过了
from the previous one. Now we got this equality here if you now
我们有了这个等式之后
open this with this definition your going to see that is identical to here.
把这个按定义展开 我们就会看到它跟这个式子是一样的
Times this. And then we got basically the formula for
还要乘以这部分 我们这样就从
the curvature of a curve that is represented in implicit form.
曲线的隐式方程得到了曲率的公式
Now pay attention this is extremely important this is going to be very
请注意这个非常非常重要
important next when I explain the forming curves in level sets.
讲到水平集上的曲线形成的时候 这就非常重要了
I don't need to have the curve I don't know c.
我并不需要知道曲线 我也不知道C
C, it's an implicit fashion define. All I need to know is phi and I take
C是一个隐式的定义 我需要知道的是 phi 函数
regular derivatives in each direction, in the Y direction.
然后我们对 x 方向求导数 对 y 方向求导数
We know how to do that. So this is the x direction, this is the y
我们知道这些方法 那么这是 x 方向 这是 y 方向
direction. We know, we just take derivatives as we
就如我们在这门课里已经见过很多次那样
have been seeing many times in this class.
我们就求导数就可以了
This pixel minus this pixel or this pixel minus this pixel when we are taking
这个像素减去这个像素 或者 用这个像素减去这个像素
derivatives in the Y direction. And we do that a number of times, just
如果要求 y 方向上导数 我们已经做过很多次了
following this formula and we get the curvature.
直接套公式我们就可以得到曲率
or we got the normal, or we got the tension, so it's much simpler, I don't
或者得到法线或者得到切线 这真的很简单
have to go and take derivatives along the curve.
我都不用沿着曲线求导
I take derivatives in the grid, basically in the image.
我们对这些格子求导 实际上是对图像求导
Really, really much simpler. So now we know the curvature, we know the
非常非常简单 现在我们已经知道了曲率 知道了法线
normals. Do we know how to deform curves?
我们知道如何使曲线变形吗？
Let's see about that. So the next step is to learn how to
让我们来看看这个 我们下一步要学习的是
deform a curve. How to deform phi in such a way that the
如何使曲线变形 如何使得 phi 变化到
boundary, basically, is deforming as I wanted.
我们希望的一个边界上去
So, we have a function that is representing a curve in implicit form.
我们已经有了一个表达曲线的隐函数
Okay? We know that the curve that is defined in
我们知道曲线是用这种方式定义的
this way, it's moving with this velocity. And we ask ourself,
它随着速率而变化 我们得问问自己
how do I have to change phi for the level set of phi to move according to this
我们如何根据这个速率来改变 phi 进而改变 phi 的水平集呢？
velocity? And it turns out that it is this form.
结果就是这个形式
And I'm going to prove to you here in just a couple of lines.
我们用几行就可以证明这个
But before we do that, please pay attention to what's happening here.
在那之前 我们需要注意这里发生了什么
The phi is once again, it lives on the image.
phi 是定义在整个图像上的
It lives on the grid. Every time I'm talking about derivatives,
它遍布于整个格子上 我每次说求导的时候
I'm talking about derivatives on the grid.
我实际上在说对栅格求导数
So the pixels are moving up or down. There's no derivatives on the curve which
所以像素实际上是上下移动 这样曲线就没有导数
are very difficult to implement. This is like when, we know.
导致非常难以实现 这就像 我们知道
We have seen how to compute a gradient. You know, again this minus this.
我们已经知道如何计算梯度 同样这里得加一个负号
We have seen those things. So implementing this is much easier than
我们知道这些东西 所以比起这个 要实现这些会更简单
implementing this. Let us prove this formula.
让我们来证明这个公式
So, the basic idea is once again very, very simple.
其基本原理还是很简单
I'm going to take the derivative of phi according to T,
我需要求 phi 对 t 的导数
okay? And this is where I'm going,
这是我要用的
I'm going to take the derivative according to T of this side, and the
我们把这边对 t 求导
derivative according to T of this side. Now this side is zero.
然后把这边也对 t 求导 这边是 0
It's a constant. So the derivative of this side is also
是一个常量 所以这边的导数还是 0
zero. Here it is.
就是这个
The derivative here, I wrote it here. And now once again chain rule, and this
这部分的导数 我将其写在这里 再用一次链式法则
is what we have. The derivative of this function of x, y,
这个关于 x y t 的函数的对 t 求导数
t according to t is what I have written here.
就得到这里的这个式子
So I take the derivatives according to x, than xt plus the derivative according to
我们先对 x 求导 然后得到 xt 加上
y, yt plus derivative according to t. These are partial derivatives.
对 y 的导数 乘以 yt 加上对t的导数 这些都是偏导数
So this is what I have. Okay, now.
于是我们就有了这个
This I moved to the other side because I have a zero here and I get minus the
我们把这个移到另一边 因为这边是 0 所以我们得到了
derivative according to t equal to the right hand.
负的这个对 t 的导数 然后等于右边的项
So this part is equal to minus this. This we have seen before,
所以这一部分等于这部分的相反数 这部分我们之前已经见到过
okay? It's an inner product as we have seen
这是一个内积
already at least two times in the previous slides.
我们在之前的幻灯片中已经至少见过两次
So it's the gradient of phi because of this part and this part.
这是 phi 的梯度 因为这一项和这一项
And this xt yt is ct is basically my curve deforming.
这个 xt 和 yt 就是 ct 也就是曲线变形
So we are here now. We have one more step.
所以我们得到了这个 我们还得继续做一步
City, I know what it is. VN so I write VN.
对于 ct 我们知道它是啥 就是 VN 所以我们写下VN
It's the motion of my curve exactly what I want.
这就是我们想要的曲线的运动
So, once again the V can come out because it is scalar and I have this.
我们可以把 V 提出来因为它也是个标量 然后我们就有了这个
Now, remember, I want to write everything as a function of phi.
现在我们想要把所有的东西都写成关于 phi 的函数
That's the important part, okay?
这部分很重要
So, we just saw that the normal is minus the gradient normalized,
我们把法线看作梯度的归一化
okay? So,
那么
here we basically applied that. We replaced minus the normal by the
我们这里就直接用这个结论 我们可以把
gradient of phi, normalized, okay?
负的法线用 phi 的梯度来替换 并且将其归一化
And this as before is gradient times gradient, that's gradient squared, divide
跟之前一样 这里是梯度乘以梯度 所以这就是梯度的平方
one gradient, we get one gradient. So this is gradient, this stays, and we
然后除以一个梯度 我们就得到了一个梯度(的模) 这些是梯度 这些不变
got this and because there's a minus here.
我们就得到了这个 因为这里有个负号
It counts as with the minus here and then we have that this is equal to this, which
于是就跟这里的负号抵消了 所以我们得到了这部分等于这部分
is what we wanted to prove. Okay?
然后就得到了我们想要证明的结论
So once again, you can look at this, if you want to just you can pause the video
大家可以仔细看看 如果大家想自己验证一下
now and look at the proof. There is nothing here but applying the
现在可以暂停一下视频来看看这个证明
chain rule, and then writing everything as a function of phi.
这里只是用了一下链式法则 并且把所有的东西都写成是 phi 的函数
That's the important part. we get that when we want to move a curve
这部分挺重要的 当我们想要根据V在法线方向上
according to V in the normal direction. That's obtained by moving feet up and
移动曲线的时候就需要这个 这是由把 phi 上下移动得到的
down, whatever this formula tells us and then we cut.
不论公式表达了什么 然后我们取剖面
So you want to go for t equal five, do this for t equal five, find the zero
如果我们想要得到 t 等于 5 的情形 那就让 t 等于 5
level set and you got the curve evolution.
找到零水平集 然后我们就得到了曲线演化
So everything now is in implicit form. We have functions defined on the plane
现在所有的东西都是隐式的 我们有这些定义在全平面的函数
and by moving those functions, we are moving the zero level set and we are
通过移动这些函数 我们移动了零水平集
getting curve evolution, for example, we're getting active contours.
然后我们就得到了曲线演化 例如 我们可以得到主动轮廓
Why is this so important? Let me just illustrate a couple of ideas
为什么这个很重要呢 让我们来看一些思想
which I think will help us to illustrate how important this is.
我觉得这些会帮助我们了解为何这个很重要
So remember, that sometimes when we deform a curve, the topology can change.
回想一下 有时候我们把一个曲线变形的时候 其拓扑也会发生变化
I'm going to ask you, which was the curve motion that produces changes in topology,
现在我来问问大家 哪一种曲线运动会导致拓扑变化
that might produce changes in topology? Is it the curvature motion, is it the
会导致拓扑上的变化 是曲率运动？
fine motion, or is it the constant motion?
仿射运动？还是法线运动？
We know that and we know that is the normal motion the normal motion can
我们知道其实是法线运动 法线运动可以改变拓扑
change topology. Now when the topology of a curve is
如果曲线的拓扑发生了变化
changing if you discrotise the curve its very difficult to understand at this
如果我们对曲线离散化 这就很难理解
point that was neighbor of this point that was neighbor of this point actually
这个点和这个点相邻
ended up here. And this one ended up there and now there
最终这个点变化到了这里 这个点变化到了这里
not neighbors anymore. They were neighbors once step before, but
于是它们就不再相邻 它们之前还是相邻的
because of topological changes they're not anymore.
但是因为拓扑变化了 它们就不再相邻了
And numerical analysis is very complicated, when those things happen,
这时候数值分析会变得非常复杂
when neighvor things, neighboring things just stop being neighboring things.
比如当相邻事件变成不相邻事件
It's very, very complicated. Now when we are in this phi function, so
非常非常复杂 现在我们有了这个 phi 函数
imagine that this gray is the phi, and basically the two planes, the two green.
想象一下这些灰色的是 phi 函数 这两个绿色的平面
Light green and dark green are just a different times you are cutting this feed
浅绿色的和深绿色的 就是在不同的时间切割 phi 函数
function. The feed function is moving according to
phi 函数根据 V 和 phi 的梯度运动
v gradient v. And all that I have to do is cut and be
我们要做的就是不断地切割
surprised if there is a topological change.
然后对拓扑的变化感兴趣
I do not have to worry about connectivites.
我们并不需要担心连通性
No worry at all, because I'm working on a grade, as I'm going to show here.
完全不用担心 因为我们是在栅格上操作 如这里所示
So I don't have to work with particles and discretizer curve.
我们并不操作粒子和离散曲线
And remember who is neighboring with whom and how the neighbor, the neighborhood is
也不用记住谁跟谁相邻
changing when there are topological changes.
以及拓扑变化的时候相邻关系如何变化
I don't have to do that. I'm basically working with phi defined on
我们完全不用做这些 我们只需要对定义在栅格上的
a grid, as we have it here. This is just another profile.
phi 函数进行操作 就像我们这里这样 这只是另一个轮廓
And phi is changing. Phi t is V.
phi 函数在变化 phi t 也就是
gradient, gradient phi and that's it.
V 乘以 phi的梯度 就这样
So we discretize that the same way that we discretized before.
我们把这个离散化 就像我们之前离散化那样
It goes up, it goes down. An example you say, I want to know the
它会上下移动 例如 我们想知道现在的
state of the curve evolution right now. You just slice it.
曲线演化的状态 我们直接切过去就可以了
You look at every place where the current phi is equal to zero.
然后我们在整个平面上寻找那些使得当前 phi 函数值为 0 的位置
You look at every coordinate or every coordinate here.
我们探查每一个坐标 或者这里的每一个坐标
If there is topological change or not you have to be aware of that.
不管有没有拓扑变化 我们能够知道
And that's the beauty of this and that is how the active counters that we talk at
这就是这个方法的漂亮之处 这就是我们在前一个视频
the end of the previous video is implemented with this where V is that
的最后提到的活跃轮廓是如何用这个实现的
velocity of active counters so V can be in a simplified fashion G curvature.
其中V是主动轮廓的速率 所以V可以写成简化形式 g 和曲率
Where G was this inverse gradient of the image or some function that makes it
g 则是图像的倒梯度 或者其他使其停止的函数
stop. So you want to implement active counters.
所以我们想要实现主动轮廓的话
All you have to do is phi t equal G curvature times the absolute value of the
要做的其实就是 phi t 等于 g 曲率 乘以梯度的模
gradient. And we know that the curvature, previous
我们从前一张幻灯片可以知道
slide, we can also compute as a function of phi.
曲率可以用关于 phi 的函数计算出来
So everything is a function of this surface that is defined on the grid and
所以所有的东西都是定义在栅格上的这个曲面的函数
that's the beauty of the level states. It simplifies the whole numerics.
这就是水平集的优雅之处 它极大地简化了数值计算
And with it we can implement the curvature motion, constant motion,
有了它我们就可以实现曲率运动 法线运动
constant motion is absolutely trivial. Let me write it here.
法线运动十分简单 让我把它写下来
Phi t equal gradient phi. So the gradient you might discretize the
phi t 等于 phi 的梯度 那么我们可以用之前讲过的
same way that we talked before. The pixel on the right minus the pixel on
同样的方法来离散化梯度 用右边的像素减去中间的像素
the center. The pixel on the top minus the pixel on
用上面的像素减去中间的像素
phi t, you discretize like phi of t + 1 -
对于 phi t 则用 phi(t + 1) 减去 phi(t)
phi of t. Any type of time discretization.
任何形式的时域离散化
We're not discussing a lot of numeric analysis like just relatively standard
我们不会讨论过多的数值分析 比如有些相对标准的数值分析方法
numeric analysis that you can use to implement.
大家可以在实现更加高明的数值分析的时候直接使用
Smart numeric analysis but relatively standard instead of having to discretize
用一些相对标准的方法来替代对整个曲线离散化
a curve. Very, very simple equations for as
一些很简单的等式
complicated as we want curve evolutions, curve motions.
就是做我们想要的很复杂的曲线演化和曲线运动
And I prove this only for curves. Happens the same four surfaces and
我只对曲线的情况做了证明 但是对于曲面来说是一样的
actually, the formula is exactly the same formula.
事实上曲面的公式跟这些公式完全一样
But phi is not function in higher dimensions so exactly the same formula.
但是 phi 并非在更高的维度里 所以公式完全一样
So, now you have the tools to do active contours.
现在我们有了做主动轮廓的工具了
And we are going to actually see more of active contours later this week in some
在这周的接下来的视频里
of the future videos. But you know curve evolution and you know
我们将会看到更多的主动轮廓 但是我们已经知道了曲线演化
how to implement curve evolution, as well.
以及如何实现曲线演化
as I said we are learning a lot of new material and as I say, you can go back
我们学了很多的新东西 大家可以倒回去再看看视频
and recheck this video. The proofs are really, really two line
这些证明都是些很短的证明
proofs with basic calculus and algebra from very, very relatively simple
其中只涉及了很简单的微积分和代数
calculus and algebra but you don't have to be aware of it. I just explain it to
大家不用关心这个
you during this video and during the previous videos.
我只是在这个视频和前一个视频里稍微解释一下
So we keep advancing and I'm going to see you again in the next video.
那让我们继续前进 希望能在下一个视频里继续看到大家
Thank you very much.
谢谢大家 【未完成版本】